Finding Aid for Woodrow W. Hunter Papers 1947-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Woodrow W. Hunter Papers 1947-1979
Hunter, Woodrow Wilson, 1913-
Professor of education, and research associate and co-director of the Institute of Gerontology of the University of Michigan. Correspondence, subject files, photographs, audio-tapes, etc., relating to his professional activities, notably his interest in gerontology and pre-retirement training.
861018
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred to the library from the Institute of Gerontology in 1985. Donor no. 6160
The collection is open for research.
Woodrow W. Hunter, born March 23, 1913, attended the University of Michigan, earning his AB in Sociology in 1937 and his MA in Sociology in 1941. From 1941-1942 he was an Instructor in Social Sciences at Central Michigan University. After serving overseas from 1942-1946, he returned to the University of Michigan in 1946 and remained on the staff until his retirement in 1978. Hunter began his work at the university as a research assistant and later research associate with the Institute for Human Adjustment. Hunter remained with the Institute through its progression: the Division of Gerontology of the Institute for Human Adjustment and finally in 1965 as a separately-established Institute of Gerontology located at the University of Michigan (Ann Arbor) and Wayne State University (Detroit). Hunter served as Acting Co-Director of the Institute of Gerontology in 1970-1971 after Wilma Donahue's retirement. From 1970 until his retirement Hunter was associate professor of education. In 1978 he retired from the university and was given the title Emeritus Professor by the Regents.
Woodrow Hunter became involved in the field of gerontology in its early period in the 19408. He was involved in a number of projects of significance in the development of this field, such as the 1947-1948 Needs and Adjustments of Older People Study, the Residential Institute program, and the Faculty Seminar in Gerontology. Hunter's most important contribution to gerontology was his research and training in the area of pre-retirement education program for the Upholsterer's International Union. He did extensive training with other companies and unions, and conducted numerous research projects and pre-retirement training programs in the U.S. and in Europe.
His professional involvement included membership in the Gerontological Society, the Adult Education Association, and the Michigan Society of Gerontology, of which he was president in 1967, and which in 1972 awarded him the Harry J. Kelly Award. He was chairman of the Education for Aging Section of the 1971 White House Conference on Aging and was involved in the planning of a number of the University of Michigan Annual Conferences.
The papers of Woodrow W. Hunter consist of ten linear feet of material and cover Hunter's thirty-two years (1947-1979) as a professor of education and researcher at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, manuscripts, course notes, data sheets, and files relating to research and training programs are included. The collection is divided into seven series: Correspondence, Training Activities, Research and Project Files, Organizations, Institute of Gerontology, Manuscripts (Not Hunter), and Other Media. Training Activities and Research and Project Files are arranged chronologically, and all others are arranged alphabetically.
Subjects:
Aging.; Aged.; Gerontology.; Hunter, Woodrow Wilson, 1913-; Retirement.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Aged persons--Health and welfare.; Gerontology.; Motion pictures.; Preparation for retirement.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Hunter, Woodrow Wilson, 1913-; Aging.; Gerontology.; Old age.; Retirement.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (1 linear foot) is subdivided into four subseries: General, Personal, Pre-retirement, and Preretirement-Government. Each subseries is arranged chronologically.
  - General 1957-1977, 19 folders (Box 1)
  - Personal 1954-1978, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Pre-retirement 1956-1979, 24 folders (Box 1)
  - Pre-retirement (government) 1956-1973, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Training activities
  Training Activities is the largest series, containing three and one-half linear feet of material. The series is arranged chronologically by year, and alphabetically within each year. The material documents Hunter's workshops, training programs, conferences, and courses, mostly on the subject of pre-retirement training. The files contain correspondence, speeches, course notes, papers, and printed materials. Training done as part of major research projects is located in Research and Projects Files.
  - Undated
    - "Gift of Life" TV Series (Box 2)
    - Lecture notes undated (Box 2)
    - Manual for discussion leaders in pre-retirement education (Box 2)
    - Notes undated (Box 2)
  - 1948
    - Ann Arbor Senior Community Club 1948-1967 (Box 2)
    - Later maturity and old age, course 1948 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Committee on Aging 1949-1961 (Box 2)
    - Living in the later years, course 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - 1950
    - "Community Participation in the Care and Treatment of Aging," 1950 (Box 2)
    - Community planning to meet needs of older people-Detroit April 1950 (Box 2)
    - Practice in social living-Grand Rapids 1950 (Box 2)
    - Living in later years-radio 1950 (Box 2)
  - 1951
    - Detroit workshop for volunteers in homes 1951 (Box 2)
    - Family living and the older person 1951 (Box 2)
    - Living in later years-northern Michigan, fall 1951 (Box 2)
    - Michigan workshop for nursing homes personnel 1951 (Box 2)
    - Problems of aging course-SW 14 1951 (Box 2)
  - 1952
    - Detroit Edison Business Club-preparing for retirement 1952 (Box 2)
    - Eaton Manufacturing Company, course 1952 (Box 2)
    - "How old is old" lecture series-Bay City 1952 (Box 2)
  - 1953
    - Delightful things to do in retirement, course-Ann Arbor 1953 (Box 2)
    - Practice in program development, course-Grand Rapids 1953 (Box 2)
  - 1954
    - Friendly visiting, course-Flint 1954 (Box 2)
    - Gerontological Society-7th Annual Meeting 1954 (Box 2)
      includes paper delivered by Hunter on community action
    - Grand Rapids agency self-evaluation project 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    - Understanding your older folks, course 1954 (Box 2)
    - West Point Manufacturing Company retirement planning 1954-1957 (Box 2)
  - 1955
    - Activities programming for older people, course 1955 (Box 2)
    - Understanding your older folks, course 1955 (Box 2)
  - 1956
    - Indiana University February 1956 (Box 2)
      includes notes and newspaper clippings from Hunter's speech
    - First Pan-American Conference on Gerontology 1956 (Box 2)
    - Niagara Falls preparation for the retirement years 1956 (Box 2)
  - 1957
    - Gerontological Society-10th Annual Meeting 1957 (Box 2)
      includes paper by Hunter on hourly wage employees
    - Aging in the modern world, course-Detroit 1957 (Box 2)
  - 1958
    - Aging in the modern world, course-Grand Rapids 1958 (Box 2)
    - Argus pre-retirement planning program 1958 (Box 2)
    - Preparation for retirement-Grand Rapids 1958 (Box 2)
    - Preparation for retirement-Toledo 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - "Pre-retirement Education Programs: How do they work?" 1958 (Box 2)
  - 1959
    - AFL-CIO community services-East Lansing 1959 (Box 2)
    - Gerontological Society-12th Annual Meeting 1959 (Box 2)
      includes paper presented by Hunter on pre-retirement discussion programs
    - ILIR/UAW leadership training program in pre-retirement education 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Education Association, planning ahead for retirement 1959 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Society of Gerontology 1959 (Box 2)
      includes paper by Hunter on retirement preparation
    - Michigan State University pre-retirement conference 1959 (Box 2)
    - "Retirement and Leisure in Industrial Society"-AFL-CIO 1959 (Box 2)
    - Seminar in social gerontology-Summer Institute 1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960
    - Seminar on preparation for retirement-East Lansing 1960 (Box 2)
  - 1961
    - Gerontological Society-14th Annual Meeting 1961 (Box 2)
    - White House Conference on Aging 1961 (Box 2)
  - 1962
    - Life is always beginning lecture series-Detroit 1962 (Box 2)
    - Owens-Illinois pre-retirement meeting 1962 (Box 2)
    - Presbyterian Village friendly visitor program 1962 (Box 2)
  - 1963
    - Michigan Society of Gerontology Annual Meeting 1963 (Box 2)
    - Untitled manuscript 1963 (Box 2)
  - 1964
    - Chrysler-UAW pre-retirement program 1964 (Box 2)
    - Dearborn pre-retirement courses 1964 (Box 2)
    - Delta College pre-retirement education program 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Governor's Conference on Senior Citizens-education task force report 1964 (Box 2)
    - Preparation for retirement-Flint 1964 (Box 2)
    - Pre-retirement education methods 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Scovill Co./UAW Local 1604-leadership training workshop in pre-retirement education 1964, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Washington State University pre-retirement workshop 1964 (Box 2)
    - "When Tomorrow Becomes Today" (TV) 1964 (Box 2)
  - 1965
    - Lockheed-Georgia pre-retirement study conference? 1965, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Pre-retirement education methods course-Flint 1965 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan pre-retirement program proposal 1965 (Box 3)
  - 1966
    - Fordham University pre-retirement leadership training project 1966, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Homemaker service course 1966 (Box 3)
    - Municipal University of Omaha retirement education methods for industry 1966 (Box 3)
    - Technical assistance workshop on Older Americans Act of 1965, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Wolverine Shoe and Tanning Corporation pre-retirement education program 1966 (Box 3)
  - 1967
    - Cooperation Between Industry, Labor, and the Community in Retirement Education," 1967 [?] (Box 3)
    - National pilot institute on education for retirement 1967 (Box 3)
    - Ontario Welfare Council pre-retirement program 1967 (Box 3)
    - Pennsylvania State University career enrichment program for Unitarian ministers 1967-1969 (Box 3)
  - 1968
    - Ann Arbor Committee for Lifelong Learning 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Caise Nationale de Retraite des Ouvriers du Batiment et des Travaux Publics (CNRO) conference 1968 (Box 3)
    - Chrysler training program 1968 (Box 3)
    - Faculty seminar in social gerontology 1968-1975, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Institute on pre-retirement counseling-Duke University 1968 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Recreation and Park Association conference 1968 (Box 3)
    - Michigan State University adult education seminar 1968 (Box 3)
    - New England leadership training program in pre-retirement education 1968 (Box 3)
    - University of Oregon seminar 1968 (Box 3)
  - 1969
    - Eighth International Congress of Gerontology 1969 (Box 3)
    - "Guidelines for Research in Pre-retirement Education," 1969 (Box 3)
    - Port Huron Council on Aging annual meeting 1969 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan pre-retirement course 1969 (Box 3)
  - 1970
    - American Association of Junior Colleges seminar in social gerontology 1970 (Box 3)
    - American Association of Retired Persons leadership training in pre-retirement education 1970 (Box 3)
    - Community care centers for old people in inner-city Detroit 1970 (Box 3)
    - Focus on tomorrow workshop for religious 1970, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Focus on your future workshop for religious 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - Gerontological Society--23rd Annual Meeting 1970 (Box 3)
      includes paper by Hunter on pre-retirement training for religious orders
    - Intercollegiate conference for committees planning training programs in gerontology 1970 (Box 3)
    - Living arrangements for the aged seminar 1970 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Society of Gerontology--13th Annual Meeting 1970 (Box 3)
    - Moreau enrichment institute for religious 1970 (Box 3)
    - National Conference on Social Welfare 1970 (Box 3)
    - New Detroit-Citizens for Better Care 1970 (Box 3)
    - Ohio Welfare Conference 1970 (Box 3)
    - Preparation for retirement--Grand Rapids 1970 (Box 3)
    - Pre-retirement for religious orders 1970 (Box 3)
    - Senior citizen forum--Marvin Esch 1970 (Box 3)
    - Shock, Dr. Nathan-visit 1970 (Box 3)
    - Social Security Administration advance planning seminar 1970 (Box 3)
    - "With This Ring," (TV) 1970 (Box 3)
  - 1971
    - Catherine B. Crippen training program for United Methodist clergymen 1971 (Box 3)
    - Generational mix retreat 1971 (Box 3)
    - GERSPPA 1971 (Box 3)
    - Meeting the challenge of the rest of your life-Sisters of St. Francis 1971 (Box 3)
    - Penafort leadership conference (religious) 1971 (Box 3)
    - Pre-retirement education course H611 1971 (Box 3)
    - Retirement planning 1971 (Box 3)
    - St. Xavier College institute for mature adults 1971 (Box 3)
    - Senior Citizen Guild of Ann Arbor pre-retirement program 1971 (Box 3)
    - Senior consumer education project 1971 (Box 3)
    - "Triple Jeopardy" symposium 1971 (Box 3)
    - United Nations-"The Aging in Urbanizing Societies," 1971 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan School of Education--50th anniversary 1971 (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan School of Nursing--growth and development II course 1971 (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw County day care center project 1971 (Box 3)
    - White House Conference on Aging-Region V 1971 (Box 3)
    - Workshops for executives and staff of state units on current issues in aging 1971, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - 1972
    - ACTION conference on the role of pre-retirement counseling for volunteer recruitment 1972 (Box 4)
    - Action for independent maturity 1972 (Box 4)
    - CNRO Board of Directors visit 1972 (Box 4)
    - Centre Internationale de Gerontologie Sociale 1972 (Box 4)
    - Challenge for tomorrow--religious retirement workshop 1972 (Box 4)
    - Changing careers: the challenge of retirement 1972 (Box 4)
    - Chrysler-UAW leadership training program in retirement education 1972 (Box 4)
    - Department of Interior forum on national outdoor recreation plan (Box 4)
    - Followup leadership training workshop for Methodist clergy 1972 (Box 4)
    - Health retirement workshop (for religious) 1972 (Box 4)
    - "How Theological Seminaries Can Better Train Their Students to Minister the Elderly," 1972 (Box 4)
    - "Leadership Training for Pre-retirement Programs in Religious Communities," 1972 (Box 4)
    - "Leadership Training of Older Persons and Others for Community Action Roles," 1972-1974 (Box 4)
    - Livingston College pre-retirement conference 1972 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Society of Gerontology--15th Annual Meeting 1972 (Box 4)
    - Midwest area student conference on gerontology 1972 (Box 4)
    - Milan Rotary 1972 (Box 4)
    - New Jersey pre-retirement program 1972 (Box 4)
    - Pre-retirement education course-H611 1972 (Box 4)
    - Programs and services in education for retirement and community organization for aging 1972 (Box 4)
    - Schoolcraft College senior citizens survey 1972 (Box 4)
    - Schools for retirement 1972 (Box 4)
  - 1973
    - Challenges of aging--First Presbyterian Church 1973 (Box 4)
    - Connecticut Department on Aging 1973 (Box 4)
    - Drake University pre-retirement planning center 1973 (Box 4)
    - Electrical Contractors Association pre-retirement education program 1973 (Box 4)
    - Gerontological Society--26th Annual meeting (Box 4)
      includes paper by Hunter on leadership training
    - Grand Rapids preparation for retirement 1973 (Box 4)
    - Japan--preretirement lecture 1973 (Box 4)
    - Kiwanis Club-Port Huron 1973 (Box 4)
    - Livonia Housing Commission 1973 (Box 4)
    - Looking forward to retirement 1973 (Box 4)
    - Northern Michigan Community College--faculty seminar (proposal) 1973 (Box 4)
    - Older persons and voluntary service 1973 (Box 4)
    - Pre-retirement education course-H611 1973 (Box 4)
    - Radio show-WUOM 1973 (Box 4)
    - Saginaw County Commission on Aging seminar 1973 (Box 4)
    - Sarason and Berken (visit) 1973 (Box 4)
    - Senior citizens day-Lakeland Community College 1973 (Box 4)
    - Serving the older adult 1973 (Box 4)
    - Summer Institute on Social Gerontology 1973, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - U.S. Army Picatinny Arsenal pre-retirement workshop 1973 (Box 4)
    - Vanderscher, Marie, and Jeanne (visit) 1973 (Box 4)
    - Wisconsin Educational Congress on Aging 1973 (Box 4)
  - 1974
    - Centre International de Gerontologie Sociale 1974 (Box 4)
    - Conference on education services for the aging and aged 1974 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Public Schools pre-retirement education 1974 (Box 4)
    - Draper, C.H.L. (visit) 1974, 1976 (Box 4)
    - First Presbyterian Church-Birmingham 1974 (Box 4)
    - Forum on pre-retirement education 1974 (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids pre-retirement education 1974 (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids Public Schools preparation for retirement seminar 1974 (Box 4)
    - Henry Ford Community College-Seminar in Social Gerontology 1974 (Box 4)
    - Looking forward to retirement 1974 (Box 4)
    - Maddison, Arthur (visit) 1974 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Society of Gerontology--17th Annual Meeting Milieu therapy treatment program 1974-1975 (Box 4)
      includes proposal and grant application
    - Northwest Michigan Regional Advisory Council on Aging 1974 (Box 4)
    - Pennsylvania State University faculty series in gerontology (Box 4)
    - Pre-retirement education conference, Jackson Community College 1974 (Box 4)
      includes grant proposal
    - Pre-retirement education course-H611 1974 (Box 4)
    - "Retirement Shock: How to Avoid It," 1974 (Box 4)
    - Smith, Eric (visit) 1974 (Box 4)
    - Statewide leadership program in pre-retirement education 1974, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Traverse City seminar in social gerontology-1974 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan faculty pre-retirement program
      - IOG-CESF staff benefits survey 1974 (Box 4)
      - Course 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - University of Connecticut--preretirement leadership training 1974 (Box 4)
    - University of South Carolina--preretirement education workshop 1974 (Box 4)
    - Van Herzeele, Dr. E. (visit) 1974 (Box 4)
    - Virginia Commission on Aging--preretirement workshop 1974 (Box 4)
  - 1975
    - Alpena Senior Citizens Center anniversary meeting 1975 (Box 4)
    - Georgia State University--planning for retirement 1975 (Box 4)
    - International Congress on Gerontology (10th) 1975 (Box 4)
  - 1976
    - Ann Arbor--looking forward to retirement 1976 (Box 5)
    - Humanistic perspectives on aging and the elderly-Hope College 1976 (Box 5)
    - Jewish vocational service and community workshop 1976 (Box 5)
    - "Leadership Training for Retirement Education," 1976 (Box 5)
      100 page manuscript written with Carl Brahce
    - Muskegon Community College--training in aging seminar 1976 (Box 5)
    - Pre-retirement education course-H611 1976 (Box 5)
    - Pre-retirement education workshop 1976 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan pre-retirement seminar 1976 (Box 5)
    - Washtenaw County Medical Society 1976 (Box 5)
  - 1977
    - Completing a vocation: retirement and the religious Life 1977 (Box 5)
    - "Innovator" article 1977 (Box 5)
    - Pre-retirement education workshop 1977 (Box 5)
  - 1978
    - Higher education and aging colloquium 1978 (Box 5)
    - National Retired Teachers Association, Mt. Pleasant 1978 (Box 5)
- Research and Project Files 1947-1979
  In general, files on research and other major funded projects are arranged chronologically in the Research and Projects Files series. Common materials include proposals, surveys, training materials, correspondence, and interim and final reports. Files from several significant research projects are included. The 1947-1948 Institute for Human Adjustment study "Needs and Adjustments of Older People" files can be found here. While never published, this study was influential in setting the agenda of the 1950 National Conference on Aging. Also in this series are two pre-retirement education studies, both of which included training. The Upholsterer's International Union Preparation for Retirement Study and Programs (1955-1956) is thought to be the first American educational program on retirement offered through a labor union and may have been the first industrial pre-retirement education program in the United States. The 1956 Niagara Falls program, "Preparation for Retirement of Hourly Employees" was a cooperative effort of management and labor of three industries, and of the community. The Hunter Papers also contain files from the 1963 Cross-National Survey of Pre-retirement Education Programs in Europe and the HEW Region V pre-retirement training project of 1976-1978.
  - Criteria for measuring effectiveness of senior citizens undated (Box 5)
  - Responses to stills project undated, includes 38 8x10 prints used in the project; also negatives (Box 5)
  - Scales and indexes-project undated (Box 5)
  - Various proposals undated (Box 5)
  - Needs and adjustments of older people 1947-1948
    - Interviews, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Manuscript, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw County infirmary project circa 1949 (Box 5)
  - Flint Committee on Aging survey of retired workers 1953 (Box 5)
  - Grand Rapids study of the needs of older people 1953, 2 folders (Box 5)
    includes 99 page printed report, "Older People Tell Their Story"
  - Upholsterers International Union pre-retirement study 1955-1956, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Evaluation, rehabilitation and utilization of work potentials of older people in county medical care facilities of Michigan 1956-1959, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Preparation for retirement of hourly wage employees in Niagara Falls, New York 1956, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Survey of university activity in social gerontology 1961 (Box 6)
  - Questionnaires (from several universities) 1961-1962, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - National Institute of Labor Education research planning conference 1962, 4 folders (Box 6)
    includes Hunter's "Background Considerations for Pre-retirement Education"
  - "Cross-National Appraisal of Pre-Retirement Education," 1963-1965
    - General (includes final report) (Box 6)
    - Belgium (Box 6)
    - Denmark (Box 6)
    - France (Box 6)
    - West Germany (Box 6)
    - Great Britain, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Italy (Box 6)
    - Sweden (Box 6)
    - Switzerland (Box 6)
  - "Survey of Preparation for Retirement Programs in Scotland and England," 1963 (Box 6)
  - "Pre-retirement Education for Hourly-Rated Workers," 1968 (Box 6)
  - Faculty seminar in social gerontology, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Manual for discussion leaders in pre-retirement education circa 1972 (Box 6)
  - "HEW Region V Pre-retirement Education Program Development," 1976-1978
    - Development, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Materials, 10 folders (Box 6)
    - Materials-Grant Proposal (Box 7)
    - Report (Box 7)
    - Final Reports, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Supplementary Documents to Final Report, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Computer Code Sheets (Box 7)
    - Computer Printout (Box 7)
      stored in Box 10
    - Bibliography (Box 7)
  - "Intra-family Cohort Study of Older Blacks," 1978 (Box 7)
- Organizations
  In the Organizations series, Hunter's involvement with a number of organizations as consultant, board member, or researcher is documented. The material is arranged alphabetically by name of organization.
  - Academy for Educational Development (Box 7)
  - Adult Education Association of the USA 1969-1974, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Centre International de Gerontologie Sociale (CIGS) (Box 7)
  - Citizens for Better Care, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - First Presbyterian Church, Ann Arbor 1967-1979
    - Committee on older members 1967-1969, 2 folders (Box 7)